Finding Aid for Richard K. Beardsley papers, ca. 1950-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Richard K. Beardsley papers circa 1950-1975
Beardsley, Richard K.
8569 Aa 2
Richard K. Beardsley was a professor of anthropology at the University of Michigan from 1947 to 1978 who served several terms as the director of the Center for Japanese Studies. The papers document his anthropological fieldwork in Japan, Spain, and California, and include research and field notes, interviews, questionnaires and surveys in English and Japanese, photographs, and a small amount of correspondence.
Sponsor: This finding aid is a product of a project supported by a grant awarded to the Bentley Historical Library and University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology in 2002 by the Division of Preservation and Access of the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.
5.5 linear feet in 6 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were transferred by Grace Beardsley (donor no. 6511 ) in 1980.
The papers are open without restriction.
Richard King Beardsley was born on December 16, 1918, in Cripple Creek, California. He received both his bachelor's degree (1939) and Ph.D. (1947) from the University of California at Berkeley.
Beardsley served in the U.S. Navy from 1942 to 1946, serving as a naval language officer in Hawaii, Guam, Iwo Jimo, and Chingtao. After receiving his Ph.D. from Berkeley, he briefly joined the faculty of the University of Minnesota. A few months later, he accepted an appointment in the Department of Anthropology of the University of Michigan as an instructor. He stayed at Michigan for his entire professional career, rising through the ranks, and was appointed as an assistant professor in 1947, associate professor in 1953, and professor in 1960. He was one of the core faculty for the Center for Japanese Studies at the university, founded in 1948, and served as its director from 1961 to 1964, 1973 to 1974, and 1977 to 1978. He also served as acting chairman of the Department of Anthropology from 1971 to 1972.
Beardsley's most well-known publication was Village Japan (University of Chicago Press, 1959), a study of the Japanese rice-growing village of Niiike, written with John W. Hall and Robert E. Ward. It was based on studies the trio conducted while in residence at the University of Michigan's field station in Okayama, Japan in the early 1950s. Beardsley returned to the area in 1973 and 1974 to conduct follow-up studies, about which he was preparing a book at the time of his death. Beardsley also co-authored Twelve Doors to Japan (McGraw-Hill, 1965), a general introduction to Japanese culture, with John W. Hall. He published a number of articles on various facets of the ethnography and archaeology of Japan, as well as several resources for the study of Japan.
While most of his field studies focused on Japan, Beardsley's early archaeological fieldwork took place in central and northern California and Mexico. He also received a Guggenheim fellowship in 1958 to conduct an ethnographic study in Valencia, Spain. Beardsley also studied several Japanese-American communities in the United States.
Beardsley was a strong advocate of increased understanding of Japan in the United States. He participated in a number of programs about Japan for the University of Michigan Television Center. He was active in the Project on Asian Studies in Education (PASE), an initiative developed by the Center for Japanese Studies to assist in the development of Asian Studies curricula at the high school and college levels. He was well-respected in Japanese and American academic and public circles and instrumental in furthering relations between the university and Japanese corporations through his participation in the East Asian Capital Campaign.
Beardsley and his wife, Grace, had three children. He died on June 9, 1978, in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
(Additional information on Richard K. Beardsley may be found in the Center for Japanese Studies records, available at the Bentley Historical Library.)
The Richard K. Beardsley Papers document Beardsley's anthropological fieldwork in Japan, Spain, and California, and include research and field notes, questionnaires, interviews, photographs, and a small amount of correspondence. The papers consist of three series: Topical Files, Research Files, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Anthropology.; Beardsley, Richard K. (Richard King), 1918-1978.; Japan--Study and teaching--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Center for Japanese Studies.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agricultural machinery.; Beardsley, Richard K. (Richard King), 1918-1978.; Funeral rites and ceremonies.; Industries--Japan.; Japan--Social life and customs.; Japanese Americans--California.; Japanese Americans--Children.; Japanese Americans--Commerce.; Japanese Americans--Dwellings.; Japanese Americans--Domestic life.; Japanese Americans--Social life and customs.; Japanese Americans--Spiritual life.; Japanese Americans--Women.; Loomis (Calif.); Photographs.; Rice plantations--Japan.; Walnut Grove (Calif.)
Genre Terms:
Field notes.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series, 1962-1974 (1 linear inch), contains folders related to two publications and the 25th anniversary of the Center for Japanese Studies' presence in Japan.
  - Center for Japanese Studies in Okayama 25th Anniversary 1974 (Box 1)
  - Japanese Reference Materials in Sociology and Social Anthropology, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Outline of Japanese Anthropology (proposed monograph), 1962-1966 (Box 1)
- Research Files, ca. 1950-1975
  The Research Files series, ca. 1950-1975 (5 linear feet), includes research materials related to Beardsley's anthropological work in Japan, Spain and Korea. Beardsley's Japanese studies are best represented in the series, which includes materials from research visits in the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s (though much of it is undated). Of particular note are the materials related to Niiike, the community about which Beardsley's seminal book Village Japan was written. The series includes research and field notes from the original study in the early 1950s, a small amount of correspondence related to the writing of Village Japan, and research materials compiled during Beardsley's follow-up visits in the 1970s. The series also includes a number of surveys and questionnaires Beardsley administered to people in various communities in Japan, including Tsushima and Kurashiki; please note that while most of the research notes are in English, many of the questionnaires and surveys are in Japanese.
  The series contains a small amount of material related to studies Beardsley conducted in Valencia, Spain with funding from the Guggenheim Foundation from 1958 to 1959. These studies were intended primarily to serve as sources of comparison for his Japanese research. The documentation includes planning correspondence and field notes. The series also includes one notebook of research on Korea from 1954.
  - Japan
    - Hirayama and Kokubunji Danchi (Box 1)
    - Kakizaki 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Kamo-Survey (Box 1)
    - Kurashiki and Kimitsu (including school questionnaires) 1970-1972, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - "Local Japan," 1974-1975 (Box 1)
      (includes autobiographical essays by Japanese young women)
    - Niiike
      - Agriculture (Box 1)
      - Autobiographical Questionnaires (Box 1)
      - Expenditures 1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Expressing Opinions (Box 1)
      - Finished Problem Sheets 1974, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Food Questionnaire (Box 1)
      - Illustration (Box 1)
      - Income Tax 1973 (Box 1)
      - Individual Attitudes and Social Values ("Chapter XIII") (Box 1)
      - Interviews 1974 (Box 1)
      - Kinship and Family 1950 (Box 1)
      - Notebooks 1950s, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Notes and Autobiographies 1950-1954 (Box 2)
      - Posters (Box 2)
      - Questionnaires 1953 (Box 2)
      - Rorschach Cards (Box 2)
      - Sociometry Charts (Box 2)
      - Songs (Box 2)
      - Statistics 1974 (Box 2)
      - Thematic Apperception Test (T.A.T.) Cards (Box 2)
      - Village Japan
        - Correspondence 1952-1954 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Okayama
      - Archaeology 1950-1953 (Box 2)
      - Notebook 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - Okayama-ken-Autobiographies of Doctors 1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Owada
      - Kin Charts, ca. 1965 (Box 2)
      - Notes 1966 (Box 2)
      - Questionnaires, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Takamatsu-Surveys (including Harakosai-Inari Survey) 1950s (Box 3)
    - Tokyo
      - Danchi Interviews 1965 (Box 3)
      - Survey 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - Tsushima
      - Notebook 1950 (Box 3)
      - Plans and Notes 1950 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Questionnaires (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 5 folders and 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Korea and Japan-Notebook 1954 (Box 3)
  - Spain
    - Correspondence 1958-1960 (Box 3)
    - Fortaleny 1959 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Village Japan Field Notes, ca. 1950-1954 (Box 4)
  - Spain Field Notes, ca. 1958-1960 (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series, 1950-1974 (0.5 linear feet), includes black and white photographs and negatives related to Beardsley's anthropological studies, mainly in Japan. The photographs are arranged loosely by subject and capture aspects of daily life in various Japanese villages and cities, as well as houses, buildings, tools, and fields. Most of the photographs are labeled. A small number of photographs related to Beardsley's study of Walnut Grove, California are also included.
  - Fieldwork in Japan 1950-1954, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Japan-unidentified (Box 6)
  - Kurashiki-Okayama
    - Automobiles and Traffic 1974 (Box 6)
    - Farm Machinery 1974 (Box 6)
    - Funerary Customs 1974 (Box 6)
    - Harvest 1974 (Box 6)
    - Housing 1974 (Box 6)
    - Industrial Development 1974 (Box 6)
    - People 1974 (Box 6)
    - Rice planting 1974 (Box 6)
  - Loomis, California 1968 (Box 6)
  - Negatives (including Kurashiki Archaeological Maps) 1950 (Box 6)
  - Okayama and Other Japan 1974 (proofs and negatives), 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Okayama ("other than Kamo area") 1950 (Box 6)
  - Walnut Grove, California, Survey Photos 1957 (Box 6)